Guide to the King Features Syndicate Cartoon Drawings and Proof Sheets 1935-1936 PR 446
New-York Historical Society
King Features Syndicate cartoon drawings and proof sheets
1935-1936
New-York Historical Society
King Features Syndicate
PR 446
3 Linear feet in 5 flat file folders
The collection holds 12 original drawings of editorial cartoons by Kenneth Russell Chamberlain and by Clive R. Weed, and 50 proof sheets of newspaper comics, syndicated by King Features. Four of the comics are from Walt Disney Enterprises. The other 46 comics are from a variety of cartoonists, written and drawn for both Sunday and daily papers. They encompass both humorous and adventure/action types of comics.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I. Editorial Cartoons (12)
Series II. Comic Strips. King Features Syndicate (46)
Series III. Comic Strips. Walt Disney Enterprises (4)
Biographical / Historical
King Features Syndicate was formed in 1915 by the publisher William Randolph Hearst, consolidating the various syndication enterprises that had formed within Hearst's newspaper businesses since they started syndication activities in 1895. The syndicate had its own staff of cartoonists, which created such characters as Popeye, featured in the "Thimble Theatre" strip. By the mid-1930s, the period represented in this collection, King Features was one of about 130 syndicates in the industry. King Features also distributed strips by cartoonists from outside the organization, including those of Walt Disney Enterprises, which is also represented in this collection. As of 2022, King Features Syndicates still exists, distributing content worldwide to over 5000 newspapers.
In 1936, some of King Features' newspaper comic strip proof sheets were exhibited at Ferargil Gallery in New York City. When the exhibition closed, the syndicate contacted N-YHS to ask if the library wanted some of the sheets for the collection. Librarian Alexander J. Wall accepted and a selection, made by King Features, was donated in April 1936. Wall asked that editorial cartoons also be donated and the twelve original such drawings in the collection were included in the gift. A few weeks later King Features sent along the Walt Disney-created sheets that are in the collection.
(The first paragraph of the above note is based on Wikipedia entries. The second paragraph is based on correspondence in N-YHS's institutional archives; see General Correspondence, RG-2, folder for letter Ki for years 1933-37.)
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift, King Features Syndicate, April 1936
Scope and Contents
The collection holds 12 original drawings of editorial cartoons by Kenneth Russell Chamberlain and by Clive R. Weed, and 50 proof sheets of newspaper comics, syndicated by King Features. Four of the comics are from Walt Disney Enterprises. The other 46 comics are from a variety of cartoonists, written and drawn for both Sunday and daily papers. They encompass both humorous and adventure/action types of comics.
Related Materials
King Features Syndicate donated its historical proof sheets in 2007 to two repositories: Billy Ireland Cartoon Library & Museum at Ohio State University and the Michigan State University Comic Art Collection.
Comic strips.; Drawings (visual works); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Chamberlain, Kenneth Russell, 1891-1984; Weed, Clive R., 1884-1936; Walt Disney Enterprises
- Series I. Editorial Cartoons, 1936
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds twelve original drawings of editorial cartoons, six each by Kenneth Russell Chamberlain and by Clive Russell Weed. Three are about high income taxes, four about other domestic U.S. issues, one about U.S. politics, three about foreign affairs, and one St. Patrick's Day-themed.
  The series is arranged by artist and then chronological. The item number used in the container list was assigned as a unique identifier at some point by N-YHS to the drawings and is found on the back of the drawing and in the Reading Room's card catalog of caricatures.
  - A leap year proposal [William Borah bid for Republican Party presidential nomination], 1936 February 29 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-12)
    Crayon drawing. Signed "Chamberlain."
  - Once a year he gets really concerned about it [Income taxes/Government spending], 1936 March 2 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-1)
  - [Above:] Let's get rid of the bad ones first! [Below:] Cruel and senseless [Deportation laws, separation of families], 1936 March 6 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-11)
  - We can stand a gentle soaking, but those hailstones hurt! [Impact of income tax in relation to other taxes], 1936 March 7 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-2)
  - "Too many monkey wrenches slow 'em up, Sam" [Efficiency of England's justice system relative to U.S.], 1936 March 9 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-3)
  - The most vital question of the hour [Scarcity of coal], 1936 March 11 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-4)
  - [Above:] Sure, oim part Irish meself! [Below:] March 17th - and Decorated!, 1936 March 17 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-5)
    Crayon drawing. Signed "Weed."
  - "What does it say about the Rhineland?" / Munition makers, 1936 March 21 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-6)
  - Haile Selassie: - "Come on, rain, do your stuff!" [Selaissie (Ethiopia) at Italy's bayonet edge], 1936 March 23 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-7)
  - Well, it's over - Until next March! [Impact of high income taxes], 1936 March 24 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-8)
  - We have something to fight, at home! [flooding], 1936 March 25 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-9)
    Crayon drawing. Signed "Weed".
  - Lilliputian [Angel of peace(?) in the armored hand of war(?)], 1936 March 26 (Folder FF-1, Item 1936-10)
    Crayon drawing. Signed "Weed." Inscribed "Dear Paul--I wish you would let Ward see this if you have time. I told him about it, Clive."
- Series II. Comic Strips. King Features Syndicate, 1935-1936
  The series holds 46 newspaper comic strip proof sheets issued by King Features in late 1935 to early 1936. These were most likely to have been among those included in the exhibition at Ferargil Gallery in 1936 from which a selection of comics was made for N-YHS (see Historical Note). 31 of the sheets are for the Sunday comics, and so are larger in size for full page publication with more panels than the sheets for the daily papers, of which there are 15 horizontal sheets. The daily sheets each include only one day's strip, not multiple days. All are black and white line art, without color.
  The container list includes all sheets/titles in the series. The cartoonist name is noted following the title in parentheses. Two entries have multiple titles separated with a slash (/); these indicate a mix of strips on the sheet (e.g., a mix of a horizontal strip and a single panel comic). Many of the strips are not titled within the strip itself, but a title and cartoonist name were noted on the reverse either by King Features or at N-YHS. The series holds a mix of humorous strips and adventure/action strips.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged roughly by format in three oversize folders. Folder FF-2 holds Sunday comics, generally of the humorous type. Folder FF-3 holds Sunday comics, generally of the adventure/action type, though the categorization is not rigid. Folder FF-4 holds daily strips, both humorous and adventure/action. Within each folder, the container list presents the titles in alphabetical order by cartoonist.
  - Little Annie Rooney (Nicholas Afonsky), 1935 December 22 (Folder FF-2)
  - Henry (Carl Anderson), 1935 November 17 (Folder FF-2)
  - The Pussycat Princess (Edward Anthony; drawn by Grace Drayton), 1935 November 10 (Folder FF-2)
  - Nicodemus O'Malley / Dreamland (Ad Carter), 1936 February 23 (Folder FF-2)
  - Just Kids (Ad Carter), 1936 February 23 (Folder FF-2)
  - Barney Google (Billy DeBeck), 1935 December 29 (Folder FF-2)
  - Little Woman (Vic Forsythe), 1936 February 23 (Folder FF-2)
  - The Katzenjammer Kids (Harold Knerr), 1936 February 2 (Folder FF-2)
  - Bringing Up Father (George McManus), 1935 December 22 (Folder FF-2)
  - Felix [the Cat] (Otto Messmer), 1936 January 5 (Folder FF-2)
  - Toots and Casper (Jimmy Murphy), 1936 February 23 (Folder FF-2)
  - Etta Kett (Paul Robinson), 1936 January 19 (Folder FF-2)
  - The Love-Byrds (Paul Robinson), 1936 February 9 (Folder FF-2)
  - Pete the Tramp (C.D. Russell), 1936 March 22 (Folder FF-2)
  - Sentinel Louie (O. Soglow), 1935 December 22 (Folder FF-2)
  - Polly and Her Pals (Cliff Sterrett), 1935 December 29 (Folder FF-2)
  - Lil Ole Orvie / Oh, Yeah? / Jimmie (James Swinnerton), 1936 March 8 (Folder FF-2)
  - Tillie the Toiler (Russ Westover), 1936 February 16 (Folder FF-2)
  - Elmer (Charles H. [Doc] Winner), 1936 March 1 (Folder FF-2)
  - Blondie (Chic Young), 1935 September 22 (Folder FF-2)
  - Heroes of American HIstory (Nicholas Afonsky), 1936 March 29 (Folder FF-3)
    Patrick Henry is the subject of the strip.
  - Ted Towers, Animal Master (Frank Buck; drawn by Joe King), 1936 March 22 (Folder FF-3)
  - Mandrake the Magician (Lee Falk & Phil Davis), 1935 November 3 (Folder FF-3)
  - Red Barry (Will Gould), 1936 February 2 (Folder FF-3)
  - Krazy Kat (George Herriman), 1935 December 8 (Folder FF-3)
    Comic strips.; Editorial cartoons.
  - The Amazing Adventures of Johnny Round-the-World: Through Djuka Lands in Dutch Guiana (William LaVarre, F.R.G.S.), 1936 February 2 (Folder FF-3)
    The panels include a photograph, the subject of which appears in one of the cartoon panels.
  - Flash Gordon (Alex Raymond), 1936 January 26 (Folder FF-3)
  - Ace Drummond (E.V. Rickenbacker), 1936 February 9 (Folder FF-3)
  - The Thimble Theatre (Elzie Crisler Segar), 1935 November 3 (Folder FF-3)
    Includes Popeye and Wimpy
  - Radio Patrol (Eddie Sullivan & Charlie Schmidt), 1936 February 1 (Folder FF-3)
  - Tiny Tim (Lyman Young), 1936 January 12 (Folder FF-3)
  - Just Kids (Ad Carter), 1936 February 18 (Folder FF-4)
  - Barney Google (Billy DeBeck), 1936 January 13 (Folder FF-4)
  - Secret Agent X-9 (Charles Flanders), 1936 March 7 (Folder FF-4)
  - Red Barry (Will Gould), 1936 January 20 (Folder FF-4)
  - Krazy Kat (George Herriman), 1936 January 3 (Folder FF-4)
  - Little Annie Rooney (Darrell McClure), 1936 February 24 (Folder FF-4)
  - Bringing Up Father (George McManus), 1936 February 13 (Folder FF-4)
  - Toots and Casper (Jimmy Murphy), 1936 February 15 (Folder FF-4)
  - Pete the Tramp (C.D. Russell), 1936 March 24 (Folder FF-4)
  - Radio Patrol (Charles Schmidt), 1936 March 12 (Folder FF-4)
  - The Thimble Theatre (Elzie Crisler Segar), 1936 March 23 (Folder FF-4)
    Includes Popeye and Olive Oyl
  - Polly & Her Pals (Cliff Sterrett), 1936 February 22 (Folder FF-4)
  - Tillie the Toiler (Russ Westover), 1936 March 10 (Folder FF-4)
  - Blondie (Chic Young), 1936 February 20 (Folder FF-4)
  - Tim Tyler's Luck (Lyman Young), 1935 December 30 (Folder FF-4)
- Series III. Comic Strips. Walt Disney Enterprises, 1936
  The series holds four Sunday newspaper comic proof sheets syndicated by King Features for Walt Disney Enterprises. These are from two series by Walt Disney, each with 12 panels. Black and white line art.
  The series is arranged by series/strip title.
  - Mickey Mouse, 1936 April 5 (Folder FF-5)
  - Mickey Mouse, 1936 April 12 (Folder FF-5)
    Donald Duck also appears in this strip
  - Silly Symphony, 1936 April 5 (Folder FF-5)
    Strip features the Big Bad Wolf and two pigs.
  - Silly Symphony, 1936 April 12 (Folder FF-5)